the dreaded continental grip anna
you have to serve with the continental
yes yes i know you like don't like it on
the server i don't like it i know i know
remember the match i was seeing you were
switching you were going to afford
okay it's double fault right
all right 30 all it's no big deal shake
it off
double faults are part of the game it is
counterintuitive you're right about that
it is mo well because when you first
start playing tennis you want to go like
this you know why
because you have this relationship
between the strings and the ball and you
want the strings to approach the ball
and that's easiest done in a forehand
grip that's why you want to go like this
when you're a beginner
it doesn't make a lot of sense or like
you said it's counterintuitive to go
like this in a continental grip with the
edge towards the ball right this doesn't
make any sense exactly but what happens
when you learn to go with the edge
eventually not yet you're still going to
go like this interestingly because you
still have a lot of muscle memory stored
but eventually you will approach the
ball on edge and then what happens is
you'll end up pronating into the contact
and that pronation to the contact is
very important on the serve so that's
why if you serve with a forehand grip
that part is going to be very difficult
to accomplish
the pronation
because the racket is going to come in
here and then out this way it's not
going to be on edge
even if you do everything else right the
forehand grip is a big mistake on the
serve now unfortunately the longer you
do it the more difficult it becomes to
get rid of it so i know it's tough but
you got to just
you know go through this period of time
where it sink where it's uncomfortable
but you have to
continue plugging away yeah that's right
it doesn't feel right
well you are actually
you were actually on eastern backhand
anna
now you're on forehand yeah there you go
i noticed one thing before you started
you were doing something so funny
i thought it was funny
yeah when you were playing when you're
playing your match you're going like
this you would go in
and then you would go like this you do
like a little hop afterwards
kind of to
kind of to propel the ball forward to
make it go over the nets
yes yes on one foot actually but uh we
gotta get rid of that
okay just the tendency
is to go fast on the bottom portion of
your serve even though the way i'm
teaching you i'm getting rid of this i'm
letting you go here right away
okay but you're going up a little too
fast here okay a little too hectic take
your time the bottom portion of your
toss motion the bottom portion of it
this
beginning motion can be done slowly and
you speed it up towards the top
slow down here and then speed up towards
the top watch slow fast
clean release anna we don't want to
flick
we don't want to flick the hand like
this we want a clean release look watch
my hand see how clean that is watch my
hand see
the palm of my hand is to the sky the
back of my hand is to the ground
clean release
it's either behind me there we go it's
okay that's the third the serve is
tricky we gotta keep plugging away
getting a continental grip
okay
no it's too low it's all right it's all
right
here's what i want you to do
i want you to hit the serve anyway if
you continue to not hit the serve the
toss is actually going to get worse yeah
what i experienced with other students
is that you it builds actually um
less confidence into your toss the more
attempts you make the less confidence
you have so go i told you this in the
match do you remember you tossed you
were tossing it way too much you were
losing confidence from there so i want
you to
make less attempts on the toss and just
hit them even if it's a bad now one
thing that you're doing here you're not
gripping the ball the ball is rolling
around your hand so grip the ball
towards the bottom portion
of your fingers okay see this
here grip it
and then release it like that
don't have it loose
you're going to release it when it which
point okay when it passes when it gets
to the level of your chin that's when
you let go
the real actual release point is going
to be somewhere between your chin and
your forehead
because it's kind of fast the release
mode so you can't really catch where
exactly it's released but in your mind
you're going to imagine releasing it at
your level of your chin
see whether you're letting go at that
particular moment or not it's not
important that's what you have to
imagine most likely you're going to let
go a little bit past the chin it's
usually around the forehead that's the
actual release point but i want you to
imagine letting go at the chin
that makes sense
it looks so easy when you do it
well because i've done it i've done it
10 million times so with practice it
gets better
that was actually pretty good but you
got a foreign grip on it yes it actually
adjusted
in the air did you see this it did i
didn't see it i had it and here it
turned well
a lot of players will go up and then
they'll go right before they drop the
racket they'll go like this
yeah let's revisit that later we don't
want to do too many things at once let's
just now focus on the toss
beautiful sirvana you liked it i like it
a lot still ended up like this but i
think i didn't see it though i it looked
correct to me it might have ended up
after after the contact yeah but that
was a nice looking toss nice looking
serve keep going that way here we go
anna you're looking better see
you start you're starting to click
don't go up so fast we don't want to go
quickly here we want to be nice and
smooth gradually accelerate okay going
from slow to fast
it's all right
by the way i don't want you to get
discouraged with the toss because the
toss is the number one problem at the
recreational level
it is such a big problem that even some
pros have trouble with it so the toss is
something that you're going to have to
have a lot of patience for
grip the ball on it don't let it loose
and you don't let it sit loose in your
hand here like this grip it come on
there you go
don't flick
see that's why i'm hesitant if i grip it
i'm not sure if i'm gonna
flick it
if i keep it open the problem with
keeping it open is gonna roll out of
your hand so if you keep it open you go
up this up movement will roll the ball
off your fingers and now the ball is
gonna have a lot of spin on it as you're
tossing there's a lot of spin that's not
good it's going to lead to
inconsistencies often the ball will also
the fingers are a little bit curled
it'll roll backwards yeah so you don't
want it loose in your hand you grip the
ball and then upon the release you let
go like this and then the ball is going
to be more flat in the air that's what i
call a flat release watch see my ball
see how it's not even spinning
see how it's flat yeah now watch if i
have a loose loose
ball in my hand and i just do the same
thing see it's spinning a lot more watch
so it's spinning a lot more yeah
it's not optimal
anna
not bad at all yeah yep do it again
best serve you hit today
fantastic job keep going we need 10 of
those okay i'm going to keep track
that's number one question why do they
do this
a lot of them they do
things like this before they serve yeah
so what does it provide for people is it
something mental and i did ever tell you
you asked excellent questions
really good question let me explain to
you why here hold on
your questions are amazing
so nice yeah basketball i can't even do
this they do something like that well
the reason why most people don't like
doing stuff handling uh tennis balls
with their left hand or if they happen
to be right-handed so that's something
that you get used to as a tennis player
but you see this right bouncing the ball
so basically what that is it's the
rhythm of the serve
okay and this is something that you're
going to do later i don't want to throw
too many things at you at once but
there's a rhythm to the serve that we
already kind of tapped into with the one
two and three remember that but
basically here slide back so you can see
it a little better
see i want you to be able to look at my
feet because the bouncing of the ball is
unimportant what happens to my feet is
important so when i bounce the ball
inside the cord you see how the weight
is on my front foot yeah so now as i
connect my racket and i start going back
the weight shifts onto the back foot
right so the bouncing of the ball can
contribute to the shifting the weight
forward
right which will then go backward and
then forward again
that's the serve rhythm so it's like a
rocking motion
so it's look it's forward forward
backward
and then back to forward
does that make sense that's why they
bounce the ball inside the court okay
but you'd have to do that now because i
don't want you to think about the rocket
motion yet we do that later we first
have to get the fundamentals right
and it starts with the toss so do a
couple more tosses so this is kind of
emphasize the quality
yeah but remember right now you're
serving stationery right i'm not having
you leave we did that a couple times but
then you took a long break from serving
you didn't serve at all like three
months or so i seriously didn't even put
any energy into service yeah so we a
little bit re so we regressed on the
serve so we have to build it back up
yeah
anna
but it was inside it's not bad at all
that one
you have to have patience otherwise
i wouldn't be fun to be around
and it would be a lot more pressure on
you you wouldn't have fun and then most
likely you quit tennis no i wouldn't be
able to if i say anna come on what's
with your touch me right now i would not
be not you better get this toss right
what's wrong with you
i know that's not bad at all that's
maybe the
slightly i'm glad you can feel that too
but that was a pretty good serve
by the way that previous server county
that is number two remember we need ten
good serves that was number two what was
it but it wasn't the other side no it
was in
not that one that was bad i'm talking
about the previous one that was your
second good one
anna
i'm proud of you
beautiful toss
all right that was number three okay
let's keep going we need ten we need ten
of these
number four
five
that's not bad at all you know what even
though it was a little bit wide i'm
gonna still give it to you because i
like the toss
all right that's number six here we go
here we go come on
anna one thing that's important that i
saw now in the last couple of tosses
your arm is kind of bending this way
yeah the left one the toss arm it's kind
of bending
you have to keep the toss arm straight
okay you don't want to bend the arm ana
you understand what i'm saying
yeah the arm is slightly bent
your toss arm so we want to keep it as
straight as possible as you're tossing
up
keep it as straight as possible
it looks more elegant that way anyway
no seriously i'm all about elegance
that's what i mean that's why i said it
way too wild the toss
it was fast the entire way
see that's interesting what's happening
now i think a lot of people the reason
why they bend the arm because they have
a lot more control when the arm is bent
generally it's because the ball is
closer to them the closer the ball is to
you the more you feel the ball when you
get a further away you have less control
so now as soon as you started
straightening the arm the ball is going
a lot faster and
really straight it's going very high but
it's going too high now it's too high
it's a little bit too speedy it tosses
too much pace on it yes so just slow it
down like 40 okay
i love that toss and that's actually an
ace it was right on the line there
that's number seven that felt good right
here we go three more
yeah would you made that sir but i
didn't like the toss
anna maybe the best serve of your life
the tempo of it absolutely phenomenal
okay good keep going that's number eight
here we go
and i love the control of that toss very
nice that's number nine here we go
match point one more good toss
bend right yeah
i say you're repositioning the ball in
your hand get comfortable with the ball
yes yeah not don't don't the tip of the
fingers here
bottom of the fingers let go yellow you
can still go on top here yeah like that
okay and here there you go because i do
it here that's a little too grippy so
it's right at the bottom of the hand not
completely on the bottom not here but
more like you see this
here you see where it's at okay
there
all right it's not here anna not here
not
here
okay okay this is somewhere in the
middle exactly
i love it number 10. that felt good
right
awesome job all right now i'm going to
get the rid of your forehand grip that's
changing somewhere throughout your serve
with a little trick okay give me one
second okay okay so the way you are
changing your grip you start off in a
continental grip and then somewhere
around here you stay there you can see
it somewhere around here you are turning
and changing
but look if i put a piece of paper
underneath my
index finger right here and now if i try
to change my grips to see the paper it's
not going to come off my racket because
it's sticking to the god
grip
hold on anna look
now in a continental grip i'm gonna put
a piece of paper right here all right
underneath my index finger and now if i
raise my finger in order to change the
grip the paper is gonna come flying
watch this
i don't know what my grip is ready
anna wait a second yeah my trick is not
working you know what it is i got a
tacky grip let me have yours yours a
little bit older it is also
hot weather so it could be sweating it's
a little bit of sweat yeah and it's
lotion on my finger sun lotion all right
so look on a continental grip just put a
piece of paper right here and now if i
let go of this piece of paper it comes
what is this like super glue paper hold
on let me get a piece of the paper this
is a dick it's just it's sticking to
your grip
hold on here
oh now
we got a paper towel okay this works too
paper towel let's see if this works i
changed my grip and oh
you came flying on you saw that yeah now
if i want to keep my continental grip
i'm going to have to hold
this grip i'm going to hold all fingers
on the grip in order to
not change it so especially the index
finger so this is a great way to control
what the hand is doing if i let go and
try to change my grip watch
it goes flying okay it works perfectly
all right try it out
anna wait a second it didn't look like
you changed your grip though
oh you did all right try it again try it
again i'm not sure when it's happening
it doesn't it doesn't actually matter
but doesn't matter if it's happening at
the very end well that would be the best
the best possible way to for it to
happen because it's happening after
contact okay
but even then i'm not a big fan of it
okay
of course it's a lot worse if it's
happening prior to the context no doubt
about it but let's get rid of that thing
anyway regardless of where it's
happening okay
ana it didn't move you know why i know
very uncomfortable well the reason why i
know it actually this might have been
the first serve today you hit with a
continental grip you know why because
the ball went like this it went to the
it went to the left
because you know what happens when you
start with a continental grip you
already have muscle memory for the
forehand grip which is this and now the
grip is turned you have that same muscle
memory at contact look at the strings
they're pointing towards the side and
now everything is going to be a slice
so this is super important that you
train your hand the muscle memory to
change so that you're turning the hand
slightly into the contact this will
happen naturally as you attempt to get
the ball into the box you're not going
to be comfortable with serving like this
the whole time so eventually you're
gonna start getting that ball more
towards the box and then naturally
intuitively that hand is gonna start
turning into the contact here try a
couple more and by the way this is not
something that it takes time to change
this
okay yeah don't don't try to
look don't worry about this area of the
serve do you just keep doing what you're
doing and try to make contact don't try
to don't try to get any ideas of what is
happening here consciously
okay do it again you move my wrist of
the on the contact
with this grip so i understand where
no just serve i'm telling you it works
this way don't over complicate it just
take a serve so it should be straight
don't over complicate it just serve
just hold a piece of paper that's your
job right now that's all you got to do
here we go
ana did it change it worked let me check
let me examine the grip
yeah you are on maybe a little bit well
no you were actually still on on
continental you were slightly over
towards the australian grip but that was
an example of where you didn't change
your grip and look
piece of paper is still there
and you had a good toss and the ball
went in
all right this is what we got to do we
got to do the paper trick until we get
rid of that forehand grip okay good work
even this is not comfortable to do with
this
grip it's funny you bring that up yeah
it's counterintuitive to go towards the
ball like this yeah so you want to go to
the ball like this and the easiest way
to go towards the ball with the strings
is to hold the racquet like this
right so when we do the racket tap from
now on let's do it in a continental grip
racket taps in a continental grip so tap
my racket
continental
there it is working
the wrist is going to be different no
doubt about it but the reason why i
don't want you obsessed about the wrist
because that part of your serve is over
in milliseconds you're not aware of what
the wrist is doing anyway so to obsess
on it and to try to figure out what the
versus position like at the moment of
contact it's useless
yeah but the risk is going to be in a
completely different position yes that's
true
but don't worry about it
good work today anna let me see the
continental grip tap
nice